JAMES J. POULIN

Houston, TX 77042
704- 763-1137
JPoulin587a@gmail.com
www.linkedin.com/in/jim-poulin/
https://github.com/jpoulin587
https://jpoulin587.github.io/jpoulin-portfolio/

Professional with Wide Experience

An experienced professional with diverse experience in many areas of business who leverages more than twenty years of experience in adult learning and performance improvement and who understands the underlying business as well as design aspects in creating learning solutions.

Compliance	Analytical Skills	Problem Resolution
Collaboration	Vendor Management	Leadership
Training	Accuracy/Efficiency	Documentation
Gap Analysis	Instructional Design	Dynamic Presentations
Troubleshooting	Health Education	Business Development

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Houston Health Department (via A1 Personnel), Houston, TX

July 2020 - Present

Contact Tracer / Data Analysis Team

Responsible for reaching out to people (contacts) who have been exposed to COVID-19 and providing health education and guidance to interrupt ongoing disease transmission.

- Initiate prompt communication with people exposed to or diagnosed with COVID-19
- Employ dynamic interpersonal skills, cultural sensitivity, tactful language, and empathetic interviewing to build rapport and maintain trust with patients of varied backgrounds.
- Conduct quality control audits of completed and in-progress cases for accuracy, completeness, and compliance.
- Working with team leads and supervisors to notify and educate staff of proper procedure.

CENTRICA/HIVE CONNECTED HOME, Houston, TX

March 2015 - October 2019

North American Technology Manager

Launched Hive North America with connected light bulbs, thermostats, plugs, sensors & cameras. Ensured all software, hardware, and mobile app release were high quality with no critical bugs.

- Designed and conducted comprehensive product training for support and sales staff covering features, user interactions, and troubleshooting.
- Provided technical education and support to commercial teams and customer support staff.
- Conducted product training to field sales teams leading to exceeding sales goals.
- Presented product demonstrations and technical consulting for potential 3rd party partners supporting Business Development and Sales teams.
- Managed North American team testing connected devices, mobile apps, and platform to ensure high quality user experience with few defects for both new rollouts and updates.

ALERTME.COM, LTD, (Acquired by Centrica 2015), Charlotte, NC Manager Environment Testing Lab, February 2013 – March 2015

February 2013 – March 2015

Led local team testing integrated IOT devices, mobile apps, and platform to ensure high quality user experience with few defects. Documented and reported issues to UK based development teams.

- Collaborated with large corporate client to facilitate user acceptance testing on new devices, new features, and bug fixes to ensure quality standards.
- Designed and conducted comprehensive product training of more than 50 connected devices.
 Audience was clients in-house call center agents. Training covered new devices / features, pre-sales support, and troubleshooting.
- Collaborated with client and UK based teams to develop new devices and features.

Manager Training Development, February 2012 – February 2013

Worked locally with UK based team that built Lowe's 1st generation "Iris" home automation ecosystem, including more 50 devices.

- Designed/developed consumer facing training for new home automation pre-sale/after sale system.
- Created and conducted client call center training for rollout of new devices and/or features.

LOWE'S COMPANIES, INC., Mooresville, NC

July 2008 – September 2011

Manager, Learning & Development - Merchandising / Business Development

Partnered with business leadership (EVP and SVP level) to understand their strategic vision and the desired state of their business, then developed plans to address skill gaps. Managed learning annual budget of \$650,000.

- Directed team conducting comprehensive needs analysis to evaluate work environment, work
 processes, and worker responsibilities to determine gaps between the leader's desired state and the
 current state.
- Developed and leveraged key business partnerships to champion change, advocate performance improvement, and provide guidance, knowledge and thought leadership.
- Managed team of Lowe's employees and external vendors to design and develop learning interventions to provide holistic learning solution for all career stages from foundational to mastery.
- Completed holistic learning architecture for General Merchants. built learning interventions to close performance gaps.
- Partnered with Real Estate, Engineering & Construction (REEC) leadership on adoption of collaborative technologies resulting in an opening of communication channels within REEC teams and with the stores.

Senior Instructional Designer - Safety Training

April 2003 – July 2008

Responsible for safety training programs for all locations (stores and supply chain) in US and Canada including New Hire Safety Orientation, Powered Lift Truck operation, and Haz-Mat.

- Coordinate with Safety department to anticipate training needs based on incident trends and changes to Lowe's policy, operational equipment and/or governmental regulations.
- Designed and implemented Lift Truck Safety & Operation training program for approximately 30,000 employees in thirty-one Supply Chain locations
- Developed online class scheduling and reporting system from a pilot program to a fully functional tool, working with vendor programmers and internal stake holders.

ADDITIONAL RELEVANT EXPERIEINCE

L.S. Training Specialist - Mohegan Sun Casino, Uncasville, CT
Technical Training Specialist/E-Learning Developer – Ames Department Stores, Rocky Hill, CT
Merchandise Allocation Analyst – Ames Department Stores, Rocky Hill, CT

EDUCATION

Full Stack JavaScript Bootcamp Rice University, Houston, TX (expected graduation November 2021)

Bachelor of Fine Arts – Technical/Design Theatre, School of Fine Arts The University of Connecticut, Storrs, CT

Clark Training and Consulting, Instructional Systems Design Certification